# Mauricio Sousa

Postdoctoral Fellow

Dynamic Graphics Project
Department of Computer Science
University of Toronto
<a href="http://mauriciosousa.github.io">http://mauriciosousa.github.io</a> | Google Scholar
mauricio.sousa@utoronto.ca

### Interests

Human-computer interaction, 3D user interfaces, virtual and tangible, collocated and remote collaboration, holograms, and mixed reality.

### Short bio

I am a Postdoctoral Fellow at the <u>DGP Lab</u>, <u>Department of Computer Science</u> of the University of Toronto working with <u>Professor Tovi Grossman</u>. Previously, I was a researcher at the <u>Visualization and Intelligent Multimodal Interfaces Group</u> (VIMMI) under the supervision of <u>Professor Joaquim Jorge</u>. I received my PhD, MSc and BSc degrees in Computer Science and Engineering. In my research, I have been designing and evaluating novel interaction techniques for the engineering, architecture and medical fields, focussing on computer supported remote collaborative work in mixed reality.

I also have experience in 3D and spatial user interfaces, virtual and tangible remote collaboration, mixed reality, fabrication, and actuated tangible interfaces applied to human-computer interaction. And I have been fortunate to see my research published in top international conferences and journals, such as ACM CHI, ACM UIST, ACM ISS, ACM IUI, ACM VRST, IEEE VR, INTERACT, IJHCS, and IEEE TVCG. I am currently a member of the organizing committee of the international conference IEEE VR 2022 and ACM ISS 2022.

## Education

#### 2020 Ph.D. in Computer Science and Engineering

Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon

Thesis: Perception Manipulation for Seamless Face-to-face Remote Collaboration

Summa Cum Laude (highest honour for Doctoral Degree)

Advisor: Prof. Joaquim Jorge

Committee: Prof. Anthony Steed, Prof. Pedro Campos, Prof. Carlos Martinho,

Prof. Miguel Sales Dias, and Prof. Pavão Martins

#### 2014 M.Sc. in Information Systems and Computer Engineering

Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon

Thesis: Remote Proxemics for Collaborative Virtual Environments

Advisors: Prof. Joaquim Jorge, and Prof. Alfredo Ferreira Committee: Prof. Carlos Duarte, and Prof. Pedro Sousa

#### 2012 B.Sc. in Information Systems and Computer Engineering

Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon

## Experience

2020 - Present DGP LAB, Dep of COMPUTER SCIENCE, UNIVERSITY OF TORONTO
Postdoctoral Fellow

Updated: July 6, 2022 Page 1 of 9

Researching, designing and evaluating novel interaction techniques, while supporting and advising undergrad and graduate students.

#### 2018 - 2020 CHAMPALIMAUD CENTER FOR THE UNKNOWN

Researcher

Researching, designing and evaluating novel mixed reality interaction techniques for minimally invasive laparoscopic surgery.

#### 2012 - 2020 INESC-ID, VISUALIZATION AND INTELLIGENT MULTIMODAL INTERFACES GROUP

Researcher

Researching, designing and evaluating novel interaction techniques in 3D user interfaces for collocated and remote collaboration using head-mounted displays, walls, tabletops, mobiles, large scale displays, and wearables. I also maintained VIMMI's <u>media lab</u>.

#### 2017/18 <u>INSTITUTO SUPERIOR TÉCNICO, UNIVERSITY OF LISBON</u>

Teaching Assistant

Human-Computer Interaction

## Students

#### **PhD Students**

2021 - Catarina Gonçalves Fidalgo, Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon, Carnegie Mellon University, Co-Advisor to Joaquim Jorge and David Lindlbauer

Thesis: TBD

#### **Master Students**

2021 - **João Simões**, Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon. Co-Advisor to Joaquim

Jorge.

Thesis: TBD

2021 - Mingxiao (Eve) Li, University of Toronto. Co-Advisor to Tovi Grossman.

Thesis: TBD

2020 - Carlos McGregor Muro, University of Toronto. Co-Advisor to Tovi Grossman.

Thesis: TBD

2020 - 2021 Manuel Lopes, Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon. Co-Advisor to Joaquim

Jorge.

Thesis: CHASM - Computer-Human Assisted Segmentation of Medical Structures

2019 - 2020 Catarina Gonçalves Fidalgo, Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon. Co-Advisor to

Joaquim Jorge.

Thesis: MAGIC: Manipulating Avatars and Gestures to Improve Remote Collaboration

2016 - 2017 Francisco Venda, Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon. Unofficial Co-Advisor to

Joaquim Jorge.

Thesis: Safe Walking in VR

2014 - 2015 João Vieira, Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon. Unofficial Co-Advisor to

Joaquim Jorge and Artur Arsénio.

Thesis: SleeveAR: Augmented Reality for Rehabilitation Using Realtime Feedback

### **Undergrad Researchers**

2022 Sixuan Wu, University of Toronto. Co-Advisor to Tovi Grossman.

2022 Angela Yang, University of Toronto. Co-Advisor to Tovi Grossman.

Updated: July 6, 2022 Page 2 of 9

2021	Tianquan (Andy) Di, University of Toronto. Co-Advisor to Tovi Grossman.
2020	Kevin Huang, University of Toronto. Co-Advisor to Tovi Grossman.

#### **Research Assistants**

2021 - 2022 Chu Li, University of Toronto. Co-Advisor to Tovi Grossman.

#### Mentoring (Ph.D. Students)

2020 -	Jiannan Li, University of Toronto.
2020 -	Laura (Di) Chen, University of Toronto.
2020 -	Fengyuan Zhu, University of Toronto.
2020 -	Karthik Mahadevan, University of Toronto.

## Academic Service

#### Senior Program Committee:

ACM International Conference on Multimodal Interaction (ICMI) 2021, 2022

#### Technical/Scientific Program Committee

International Conference on Graphics and Interaction (ICGI) 2021, 2022

IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality (ISMAR) 2021

ACM International Conference on Multimodal Interaction (ICMI) 2020

#### **Organizing Committee:**

Workshop: Enhancing Cross-Reality Applications and User Experiences In International Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces (AVI) 2022

ACM International Conference on Interactive Surfaces and Spaces (ISS) 2020, 2022

IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces (VR) 2021, 2022

Eurographics

2016

#### **Conference Session Chair:**

ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST) 2021

#### Peer Reviewer:

IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality (ISMAR) 2017, 2018, 2019, 2020, 2021, 2022

Updated: July 6, 2022 Page 3 of 9

ACM International Conference on Interactive Surfaces and Spaces (ISS)

2016, 2017, 2018, 2019, 2020, 2022

ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)

2018, 2020, 2021, 2022

ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST)

2020, 2021, 2022

ACM Conference on Designing Interactive Systems (DIS)

2016, 2021

International Conference on Graphics and Interaction (ICGI)

2021

ACM Symposium on Spatial User Interaction (SUI)

2017, 2020

ACM Symposium on Virtual Reality Software and Technology (VRST)

2017, 2018, 2020

ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW)

2020

Elsevier Computers & Graphics

2018, 2019, 2020

ACM International Conference on Tangible, Embedded and Embodied Interaction (TEI)

2018, 2020

ACM ACM International Conference on Multimodal Interaction (ICMI)

2018, 2019

IEEE Consumer Electronics Magazine (CEM)

2016

## Full list of Publications

20 conference proceedings, 6 journal articles 470+ citations, h-index 14 (Google Scholar)

#### Peer-reviewed Conference Proceedings

c20 immersivePOV: Filming How-To Videos with a Head-Mounted 360° Action Camera.

Kevin Huang, Jiannan Li, Maurício Sousa, and Tovi Grossman. ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), 2022.

\* Honorable Mention Award

C19 ASTEROIDS: Exploring Swarms of Mini-Telepresence Robots for Physical Skill Demonstration. Jiannan Li, Maurício Sousa, Chu Li, Jessie Liu, Yan Chen, Ravin Balakrishnan, and Tovi Grossman. ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), 2022.

Updated: July 6, 2022 Page 4 of 9

- C18 Route Tapestries: Navigating 360° Virtual Tour Videos Using Slit-Scan Visualizations.

  Jiannan Li, Jiahe Lyu, Maurício Sousa, Ravin Balakrishnan, Anthony Tang, and Tovi

  Grossman. ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST), 2021
- C17 Promoting Reality Awareness in Virtual Reality through Proxemics. Daniel Medeiros, Rafael dos Anjos, Nadia Pantidi, Kun Huang, Maurício Sousa, Craig Anslow and Joaquim Jorge. IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces (IEEE VR), 2021.
- C16 "Grip-that-there": An Investigation of Explicit and Implicit Task Allocation Techniques for Human-Robot Collaboration. Karthik Mahadevan, Maurício Sousa, Anthony Tang, and Tovi Grossman. ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), 2021.
  \* Honorable Mention Award
- C15 Negative Space: Investigating Workspace Awareness in 3D Face-to-face Remote Collaboration. Maurício Sousa, Daniel Medeiros, and Joaquim Jorge. ACM SIGGRAPH International Conference on Virtual-Reality Continuum and its Applications in Industry (VRCAI), 2019
- C14 Safe Walking in VR. Maurício Sousa, Daniel Medeiros, and Joaquim Jorge. ACM SIGGRAPH International Conference on Virtual-Reality Continuum and its Applications in Industry (VRCAI), 2019
- C13 Adventures in Hologram Space: Exploring the Design Space of Eye-to-eye Volumetric Projection-based Telepresence. Rafael Kuffner dos Anjos, Maurício Sousa, Daniel Medeiros, Daniel Mendes, Mark Billinghurst, Craig Anslow and Joaquim Jorge. ACM Symposium on Virtual Reality Software and Technology (VRST), 2019
- C12 WARPING DEIXIS: Distorting Gestures to Enhance Collaboration. Maurício Sousa,
  Rafael Kuffner Dos Anjos, Daniel Mendes, Mark Billinghurst, and Joaquim Jorge. ACM
  Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), 2019
  \*Featured in the 'Best of CHI 2019' event by IndiaHCI
- C11 Using Custom Transformation Axes for Mid-Air Manipulation of 3D Virtual Objects.

  Daniel Mendes, Maurício Sousa, Rodrigo Lorena, Alfredo Ferreira, and Joaquim Jorge.

  ACM Symposium on Virtual Reality Software and Technology (VRST), 2017
- C10 Creepy Tracker Toolkit for Context-aware Interfaces. Maurício Sousa, Daniel Mendes, Rafael Kuffner dos Anjos, Daniel Medeiros, Alberto Raposo, Alfredo Ferreira, João Pereira, and Joaquim Jorge. ACM Interactive Surfaces and Spaces (ISS), 2017
- C9 VRRRRoom: Virtual Reality for Radiologists in the Reading Room. Maurício Sousa, Daniel Mendes, Soraia Paulo, Nuno Matela, Joaquim Jorge, and Daniel S. Lopes. ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), 2017
- C8 PRECIOUS! Out-of-reach Selection using Iterative Refinement in VR. Daniel Mendes, Daniel Medeiros, Eduardo Cordeiro, Maurício Sousa, Alfredo Ferreira, and Joaquim Jorge. IEEE Symposium on 3D User Interfaces (3DUI), 2017

Updated: July 6, 2022 Page 5 of 9

- C7 Mid-air Modelling with Boolean Operations in VR. Daniel Mendes, Daniel Medeiros, Maurício Sousa, Ricardo Ferreira, Alberto Raposo, Alfredo Ferreira, and Joaquim Jorge. IEEE Symposium on 3D User Interfaces (3DUI), 2017
- C6 Effects of Speed and Transitions on Target-based Travel Techniques. Daniel Medeiros, Eduardo Cordeiro, Daniel Mendes, Maurício Sousa, Alberto Raposo, Alfredo Ferreira and Joaquim Jorge. ACM Symposium on Virtual Reality Software and Technology (VRST), 2016
- C5 **Perceiving Depth: Optical versus Video See-through.** Daniel Medeiros, Maurício Sousa, Daniel Mendes, Alberto Raposo, and Joaquim Jorge. ACM Symposium on Virtual Reality Software and Technology (VRST), 2016
- C4 SleeveAR: Augmented Reality for Rehabilitation using Realtime Feedback. Maurício Sousa, João Vieira, Daniel Medeiros, Artur Arsenio, and Joaquim Jorge. ACM Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI), 2016
- C3 From Tecton to Teknos: Going back to the Classical Roots of Architecture. Daniel Mateus, Maurício Sousa, Rui de Klerk, Sandra Gama, Joaquim Jorge, and José Duarte. Education and Research in Computer Aided Architectural Design in Europe (eCAADe), 2015
- C2 **Eery Space: Facilitating Virtual Meetings Through Remote Proxemics.** Maurício Sousa, Daniel Mendes, Alfredo Ferreira, João Madeiras Pereira, and Joaquim Jorge. Human-Computer Interaction—INTERACT, 2015
- C1 Beyond Post-It: Structured Multimedia Annotations for Collaborative VEs. João Guerreiro, Daniel Pires, Maurício Sousa, Daniel Mendes, Ismael Santos, Alberto Raposo, and Joaquim Jorge. Eurographics Symposium on Virtual Environments (EGVE), 2014

#### **Journal Articles**

- J6 Laparoscopy with Augmented Reality Adaptations. Ezequiel Zorzal, José Miguel Gomes, Maurício Sousa, Pedro Belchior, Pedro G da Silva, Nuno Figueiredo, Daniel S. Lopes, and Joaquim Jorge. Elsevier Journal of Biomedical Informatics, 2020
- J5 Anatomy Studio: a Tool for Virtual Dissection Through Augmented 3D Reconstruction Sessions. Ezequiel Zorzal, Maurício Sousa, Daniel Mendes, Rafael K dos Anjos, Soraia F. Paulo, Pedro Rodrigues, José Mendes, Vincent Delmas, Jean-Francois Uhl, José Mogorrón, Daniel S. Lopes, and Joaquim Jorge. Computers & Graphics, 2019
- J4 Magic Carpet: Interaction Fidelity for Flying in VR. Daniel Medeiros, Maurício Sousa, Alberto Raposo, and Joaquim Jorge. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (TVCG), 2019
  - \* Recipient of the Encarnação Award 2020 from Eurographics Portuguese chapter

Updated: July 6, 2022 Page 6 of 9

- Design and evaluation of novel out-of-reach selection techniques for VR using iterative refinement. Daniel Mendes, Daniel Medeiros, Maurício Sousa, Eduardo Cordeiro, Alfredo Ferreira, and Joaquim Jorge. Computers & Graphics, 2017
   Honourable Mention in the 33rd Spring Conference on Computer Graphics
- J2 Hip-directed walking-in-place using a single depth camera. Luís Bruno, Maurício Sousa, Alfredo Ferreira, João Madeiras Pereira, and Joaquim Jorge. International Journal of Human-Computer Studies (IJHCS), Elsevier, 2017
- J1 Expeditious Illustration of Layer-Cake Models On and Above a Tactile Surface.

  Daniel S. Lopes, Daniel Mendes, Maurício Sousa, and Joaquim Jorge. Computers & Geosciences (in press), 2016

#### **Book Chapters**

- B2 A Tool for Collaborative Anatomical Dissection. Ezequiel Zorzal, Maurício Sousa, Daniel Mendes, Soraia Paulo, Pedro Rodrigues, Joaquim Jorge, and Daniel Simões Lopes. Book chapter in Digital Anatomy, Springer, 2021
- B1 Remote Proxemics. Maurício Sousa, Daniel Mendes, Daniel Medeiros, Alfredo Ferreira, João Madeiras Pereira, and Joaquim Jorge. Book chapter in Collaboration Meets Interactive Spaces, Springer, 2016

#### Other Peer Reviewed Publications

- O12 Anatomy Studio II: A Cross-Reality Application for Teaching Anatomy. Joaquim Jorge, Pedro Belchior, Abel Gomes, Maurício Sousa, João Pereira, and Jean-François Uhl. XR for Healthcare and Wellbeing Workshop Workshop (IEEE VR), 2022
- O11 Design requirements to improve laparoscopy via XR. Ezequiel R Zorzal, Maurício Sousa, Pedro Belchior, João Madeiras Pereira, Nuno Figueiredo, and Joaquim Jorge. XR for Healthcare and Wellbeing Workshop Workshop (IEEE VR), 2022
- O10 Constellation: a Multi-User Interface for Remote Drone Tours. Jiannan Li, Maurício Sousa, Ravin Balakrishnan, and Tovi Grossman. International Conference on Human-Agent Interaction (HAI), 2021
- O9 Demo hour. Paden Shorey, Audrey Girouard, Sang Ho Yoon, Yunbo Zhang, Ke Huo, Karthik Ramani, Maurício Sousa, Daniel Mendes, Soraia Paulo, Nuno Matela, Joaquim Jorge, Daniel S. Lopes, Dirk Wenig, Johannes Schöning, Alex Olwal, Mathias Oben, and Rainer Malaka. Demo hour. interactions 24, 6 (October 2017), 8-11.
- O8 Evaluation of Travel Techniques for Virtual Reality. Eduardo Cordeiro, Daniel Medeiros, Daniel Mendes, Maurício Sousa, Alberto Raposo, Alfredo Ferreira, and Joaquim Jorge. Portuguese Meeting of Computer Graphics (EPCG), 2016
- O7 Beyond Eery Space: Applying Gradual Engagement to Remote Proxemics. Maurício Sousa, Daniel Medeiros, Alberto Raposo, and Joaquim Jorge. Collaboration meets Interactive Surfaces Workshop, ACM Interactive Tabletops and Surfaces(ITS), 2015

Updated: July 6, 2022 Page 7 of 9

- O6 Augmented Reality for Rehabilitation Using Multimodal Feedback. João Vieira, Maurício Sousa, Artur Arsénio, and Joaquim Jorge. REHAB2015 Workshop, 2015
- O5 Enabling Remote Proxemics through Multiple Surfaces. Daniel Mendes, Maurício Sousa, João Madeiras Pereira, Alfredo Ferreira, and Joaquim Jorge. Collaboration meets Interactive Surfaces Workshop, ACM Interactive Tabletops and Surfaces(ITS), 2014
- O4 **Eery Proxemics: Proximidade à Distância usando Múltiplas Superfícies**. Maurício Sousa, Daniel Mendes, João Madeiras Pereira, Alfredo Ferreira, and Joaquim Jorge. Portuguese Meeting of Computer Graphics (EPCG), 2014
- O3 ThumbCam: Returning to single touch interactions to explore 3D virtual environments.

  Daniel Mendes, Maurício Sousa, Alfredo Ferreira, and Joaquim Jorge. ACM Interactive
  Tabletops and Surfaces(ITS), 2014
- O2 Binding a Handheld Device with its Owner. Maurício Sousa and Joaquim Jorge.
  Collaboration meets Interactive Surfaces Workshop, ACM Interactive Tabletops and Surfaces(ITS), 2013
- O1 Collaborative 3D Visualization on Large Screen Displays. Daniel Mendes, Maurício Sousa, Bruno Araújo, Alfredo Ferreira, Hildegardo Noronha, Pedro Campos, Luciano Soares, Alberto Raposo, and Joaquim Jorge. Powerwall Workshop, SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems(CHI), 2013

#### Workshops

W1 Enhancing cross-reality applications and user experiences. Frank Maurer, Craig Anslow, Joaquim Jorge, and Mauricio Sousa. International Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces (AVI), 2022

#### **Theses**

- T2 Perception Manipulation for Seamless Face-to-face Remote Collaboration.

  Maurício Sousa. Ph.D. Thesis. Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon. 2020
- T1 Remote Proxemics for Collaborative Virtual Environments. Maurício Sousa. M.Sc. Thesis. Instituto Superior Técnico, University of Lisbon. 2014

## Awards and Recognitions

#### Best Paper Honorable Mention Award ACM CHI 2022

[C20] immersivePOV: Filming How-To Videos with a Head-Mounted 360° Action Camera.

#### Recognition of Service Award IEEE VR 2022

In appreciation for contributions to IEEE VR Conference as Web Chair

Best Paper Honorable Mention Award ACM CHI 2021

Updated: July 6, 2022 Page 8 of 9

[C16] "Grip-that-there": An Investigation of Explicit and Implicit Task Allocation Techniques for Human-Robot Collaboration.

Paper selected to feature in the 'Best of CHI 2019' event by IndiaHCI [C12] WARPING DEIXIS: Distorting Gestures to Enhance Collaboration.

Paper recipient of the Encarnação Award 2020 from Eurographics Portuguese chapter [J4] Magic Carpet: Interaction Fidelity for Flying in VR.

Honourable Mention Award in the 33rd Spring Conference on Computer Graphics 2017 [J3] Design and evaluation of novel out-of-reach selection techniques for VR using iterative refinement.

## References

Available upon request.

Updated: July 6, 2022 Page 9 of 9